this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program Robert bloomin
I'm here at Q con San Francisco o 9 with
Jake reps of project Voldemort J welcome
to software engineering radio hey thank
you very much for having me it's a
pleasure to be here tell the listeners a
little bit about your background yes oh
so I guess I have been involved in like
data related programming problems for
websites I used to work for a comparison
shopping site called nextag and now I
work for LinkedIn social network and so
originally my interest and educational
background was was more in machine
learning applications but I found that
more and more I was pulled just into
scalability problems and so one of the
things that I worked on it at LinkedIn
was this project Baltimore which is a
storage system so it's it's you know
purely a distributed application it has
no kind of analytical applications it's
just for you know storing your data and
getting it back out and it's it's
something we've put used there for these
these projects so what is project Volta
more so it's a distributed storage
system so it's it's kind of like a
dumbed down version of my sequel or any
database but it supports much much
weaker queries and will scale across
many machines so so will support much
much larger data and much higher rate of
course give us a brief history of the
project so I started the project
actually right about the time I came to
LinkedIn at that time LinkedIn didn't
really have any distributed storage
solution we just had databases
centralized databases some some caching
in front of them sometimes but but that
was it so I thought you know there was
there was room for improvement and then
we had a lot of projects which you know
required storing a lot of data or
required serving a lot of data and when
you have only a single database that can
be there can be a big challenge because
you're trying to store much more data
than you have memory provide a brief
history of the project so it's
project Baltimore was something I
started working on right about the time
I came to LinkedIn we had a number of
problems that I thought this would be
applicable for so it seemed like a good
thing to do it wasn't really officially
a project of Lincoln's it was more like
you know a 20% project but it became
kind of an official project as more and
more applications came around there are
a lot of popular databases out there
obviously you thought that none of them
really solved the problem you've had
tell us a bit about what is the unique
problem domain that you think Voldemort
solves that wasn't adequately solved by
other tools it already existed sure so
there are a lot of good oven source
databases the there's kind of two
categories there's there's fairly stable
well tested systems like my sequel or
Postgres which are centralized database
systems so they do a great job on a
single computer and they provide you
know very rich query capabilities and a
lot of features those were not what we
were looking for because we needed we
needed to scale you know over many
computers and doing that on top of those
systems is somewhat difficult so that
was that was the problem we were trying
to solve now recently there's been a lot
more distributed databases and so this
is in that space it's a very new space
there's a lot of a new project every
week could you name some of the other
well-known projects in that space
there's a whole kind of no sequel genre
I guess of open source projects it
breaks down into a couple different
areas but but people who are doing your
real-time distributed storage there's
also Cassandra there's HBase there's
there's there's a number of other ones a
lot of people are trying to solve this
problem at the same time this must be an
emerging problem what real-world factors
have driven the emergence of this
problem probably the most obvious thing
is actually quite obvious which is the
the internet right so the internet one
of the things it ends up doing is
centralizing a lot of computation it's
kind of the opposite of what you would
expect you to expect if you expected
computers with fast networks that you
would decentralize computation but in
fact it means that everybody wants to go
to Google or they want to go to
or they want to go to some other website
and they want that company to do some
computation for them which means that
you end up having millions of users
coming coming to your site every day
wanting to do some computation which
which creates a huge load problem right
so if if you imagine the larger
applications you know before that we're
probably Enterprise application you
could imagine having hundreds of people
all using it at the same time but it was
still just a few hundred people I didn't
really warrant you know changing the
architecture of a database just support
that you just bought a slightly bigger
machine
so that that's the main force the other
forces you know things are changing
discs are getting slower programming
languages have become safer so you don't
necessarily need a specialized query
language there's a lot of other factors
but but I think the main one is just the
the demand for more scalability in your
talk at Q Khan you said something very
interesting
80% of caching tears are fixing problems
that shouldn't exist what did you mean
by that there's two things you can cache
right one is you can put a cache in
front of your database meaning you you
pull something out of the database and
you put it in your cache the problem
with that is your your database is also
a cache right your your database
machines have a bunch of memory and your
caching machines probably have also a
bunch of memory and probably you have
the same stuff in both systems so that's
that's kind of a bad it's a bad solution
you could have twice as much memory say
now there's there's another kind of
caching which is you know maybe you have
pulled together many different things
from different databases and you've done
a lot of computation on top of it and
you want to cache that result that makes
a lot of sense right you don't want to
redo that computation if you can help it
so that's that's what I meant is it most
the time when people are using caching
they're just pulling something out of a
database putting it in a cache and then
looking in the cache again and really
that's a problem that database should
solve you hadn't shouldn't have to build
a storage system on top of your storage
system to make it faster so would it be
fair to project the voldemort is a
replacement for what people are doing
now in a lot of sites with a sharded
relational database some read replicas
and some memcache D servers yes yeah
that is the goal is to replace that kind
of a setup primarily you
cost savings or is there something else
driving in um yeah so you would hope to
get a couple things like one is
simplicity and not having to build that
if you have to build the layer that
deals with caching and deals with
partitioning and deals with you know
migrating of shards back and forth and
all that kind of stuff it's a lot of
work this provides you something which
is you know somewhat simpler you can
kind of mock it out for your testing you
can you know a lot of these problems are
solved and and in an Edition we would
hope it would be you know faster because
we were able to drop some of the
features that we don't need and you know
support simpler the simpler queries you
would be doing in that partition system
anyway so there should be some cost
savings and performance improvement as
well when you built this similar
projects did not exist but were you
influenced by some other things that
were already out there that you liked
yeah probably the biggest influence was
the Google BigTable and Amazon dynamo
papers so the the BigTable was just a
very popular system so so design wise
there's not that many similarities the
the similarities are mostly to this this
Amazon dynamo system so those both
existed only as you know published
computer science papers there's nothing
we'd ever used because they're you know
proprietary systems so that was the goal
was to provide something like that that
you could download off the internet and
use what are some typical use cases for
project Voldemort so what I've seen and
what we're doing at LinkedIn is is
primarily things that are under
scalability pressure so there's there's
a there's a couple ways I guess how
storage problem can be hard one is you
know it could be financial transactions
you could you could be very important
that you have precise consistency it
could be very important that you never
lose the data there's other problems
which are primarily just about you know
reading the data as fast as possible
so we're we're primarily you know
focusing on problems that have a lot of
scalability pressure could be very very
simple storage problems so you know we
use it for tracking activity data that
helps us do relevant features it helps
us do you know anything else like that
but it but it does required doing or
bright you know you know multiple times
for each page that's served on the side
and so that's that's a very scalability
intensive problem to solve so so those
are the kinds of things that we've
looked at first primarily because we had
no other way to solve those problems
whereas some smaller problem that you
know you can still just put everything
in a my sequel instance or Oracle
instance and you know it will certainly
work for for something it's primarily
driven by the size of the problem yeah
that's right that's right
cases where you wish you could use a
relational database because you're very
unhappy to give up all the
general-purpose query functionality but
you're really forced to go this way
because of scale yeah so so probably all
of them so I think I think the the
comparison for us is really you know
when we're using a relational database I
think it's usually an extremely dumbed
down way so compared to that one of
these no sequence terms like Baltimore
is much nicer to use but compared to you
know how you might use a relational
database with an ORM system on top of it
if you were building just a very small
application that's very convenient
because you make no commitments about
how you access your data you know
probably all of your data will fit in
memory on the database and it provides a
very flexible solution now now once
you're either putting things on disk you
know on a centralized system or or
spreading them across machines in a
decentralized system you're gonna have
to make choices about how you access
your data and that that's gonna make it
a much much harder to use at that point
I think it becomes a good trade-off if
you don't need to do that then I think
you know the probably there's nothing
about I sequel you're you're unhappy
with unless you just don't like you know
the sequel query language so if I'm
using Project Voldemort and I need to
look something up based on secondary key
that poses a little bit more of a
difficulty yes I mean the way these
systems work is you push all that logic
for different lookups into the right so
when you're doing or right you're gonna
need to update a secondary list of items
that points to it so if you have maybe
users by a primary user ID and you have
users by an email you're gonna have to
up
both and you're gonna have to deal with
the fact that they could be slightly out
of sync because those updates don't
happen in a single transaction right so
meaning when you fetch by primary key
you always get the up-to-date result but
when you fetch by email it could be a
few milliseconds behind and you'll have
to deal with the fact there's somebody
updated their email right at that
instant then you get back no results
when you fetch you know you have to
handle that correctly in your
application so it's a trade-off I think
what you're saying is because of these
scale issues the programming model that
we've all come to know and love where
the data store appears as this mass of
undifferentiated centralized data that
that illusion is really going away and
as programmers we're gonna have to deal
with some of the things we wish we
didn't have to deal with like the
structuring of the data and underlying
consistency problems of a distributed
system yes so that's that's true I mean
the the hope with these systems is
actually to paper over it as much as
possible so that you don't deal with
those now you end up thinking about how
to do things with a weaker query model
rather than thinking about oh how many
machines are we gonna have in production
when we release this butBut my
experience has been that you end up
thinking a lot about what the database
is doing if the data is large no matter
what you'll spend a lot of time thinking
about how is Oracle answering this this
query what is it doing you're gonna
spend a lot of time you know testing
that even if you're using a very
traditional database right you have to
think through that otherwise your your
product won't work Voldemort provides a
weaker consistency model than what most
of us are used to with the relational
database first tell us what is the
consistency model that relational
databases provide sure so I mean the
idea of consistency is is you know kind
of when you ask a question what
guarantees about the answers you have so
traditionally for databases the you know
you're talking about acid which is you
know kind of atomic consisted isolated
durable so so what does that mean it
means essentially that when you when you
do some operation your operation will
either happen or not we're talking about
a right you know if you if you never
write to your data then it's kind of
very easy to keep it consistent you just
you just put
everywhere but the problem the
fundamental problem that we're trying to
solve is if you have more than one
machine and you do a write to one
machine you then need to do the same
right maybe to another machine to keep
the two in sync and of course those
can't happen at the same instant in time
so all of the problems that come up in
these systems does you know how to make
it appear as if it happened at the same
time what's the best you can do so for a
traditional database that you don't have
that problem you have only a single
machine you you can you can simply lock
around the update in memory which which
makes it appear that it either happens
or doesn't right so so the properties
that you get is that you know it's it's
atomic meaning it happens or it doesn't
it's it's it's isolated it's durable
meaning you know it's written to disk in
practice but but particularly that it's
that it's consistent meaning you know
you you get the same answer twice you
talk you discussed academic research
called the cap theorem which showed in a
formal way how this consistency property
cannot be extended to scale tell us a
little more about that
sure so there's a there's a couple of
these impossibility of results so it's
always funny when these something you
know a proof of impossibility becomes a
practical topic because you know all it
does is prove that you can't do
something in a certain mathematical
model so that cap theorem is one of
these results I don't know if it's the
most fundamental one but it's the one
that has been made the most sense to
people so so what it's saying is it kind
of goes along with acid it's talking
only about a distributed system meaning
you have state on more than one machine
and what it's telling you is that you
have to choose between consistency
availability and partition tolerance you
know in particular you can get you can
get two of those but not all three
so part you don't get consistency is is
is the same as in the case of acid
availability is the you know is can you
get at your data right so it's very easy
to to provide consistency and partition
tolerance if you don't have availability
because you can just shut down the
system anytime there's a problem
so that's that's an easy way to get to
the one that's that's a little bit
tricky as partition tolerance so this is
something which is they're not that well
understood but the idea is the the
simplest idea is what if what if you had
you know three machines here and on one
network and three machines on another
network and they suddenly couldn't talk
to each other how are you going to be
able to take updates on one set of
machines or the other right because you
can't keep the same state and sync
between them now that problem becomes is
not just a you know what if there was a
problem with the network but also you
know in any case where you're taking an
update on one machine it may have some
idea of what other machines are
currently working and currently not
working
how can you correctly propagate that
update if everyone doesn't agree on
which machines are working and not
working and so the key problem is can
you tell which machines are working and
not working it depends right so it's
it's it's very finicky problem in
practice people are kind of detecting it
meaning they're they're guessing so so
that's that's the fundamental problem so
people have proven you know in some
mathematical settings that you can have
it best to of this and that's I think
motivating a lot of the more relaxed
consistency models that you see for
these newer distributed databases we
would all as application developers like
to have strong consistency now as we're
learning we can't really have everything
we want you have to weaken the
consistency model in such a way that you
can still provide a reasonable user
experience so what are some of the
directions you would go with that sure
so so I think eventual consistency is
the idea that you know your your data
will come in to consistency but but
maybe not immediately upon the instant
of the right so so clearly the the
weakest guarantee is that you it will
someday happen weaker still is no
guarantee of consistency meaning you
know hopefully it will happen but if if
some server crashes or something then
there's absolutely no guarantee at all
all right so so Baltimore and a lot of
these more kind of systems that are
they're modeled on Amazon dynamo try to
provide something better than that
so in particularly they try to provide
two guarantees about being able to read
your own rights
so so it's it's tunable you can make it
faster by having less consistency or you
or you can make it a little a little bit
slower still not slow but but somewhat
slower with with better consistency so
the guarantee you can give is
essentially around reading your own
rights meaning if you did an update you
want to get that back so in practice
this means you know if I enter some
information on our form on a website and
I hit submit on the next page when you
show me what I just entered and you ask
me to confirm I better get back the same
thing I put into the form or I'll be a
very confused user and so so I think you
have to be able to provide at least that
otherwise you provide a pretty bad user
experience
if this inconsistency stuff happens at
all frequencies frequently if it's one
in a million maybe you'd say well that
user will be a bit confused but it very
rarely happens I don't know but but we
can provide that kind of read your own
rights consistency which i think is the
guarantee most people are looking for so
if I enter a comment on a blog somebody
else does a read of the blog comments
are you saying we don't necessarily care
if that guy is 300 milliseconds behind
the most recent blog comment yeah so you
can get into a lot you can you can think
of a lot of scenarios where consistency
is not as important and so things like a
search system will almost always take
advantage of this so if you if you enter
a comment on a blog it may actually be
you know a minute before you're able to
find that in a search because you know a
search index needs to be updated with
this the more you update the index the
more inefficient the system is so in
fact you know a lot of things you're
doing that already so yeah that's that's
exactly the idea is that you know in
some cases you don't need as strong as
you know read you're right consistency
you just need I get the update pretty
soon now in practice pretty soon is
gonna be pretty soon like you know less
than a second it's not it's not you know
20 minutes so we're forced by the growth
of data and scale in these web
applications to weaken the consistency
model we're learning that this really
strong guarantee of consistency was a
little bit over engineered for some
cases where it wasn't really required if
you need it you need
there's no there's no arguing with that
right if you have an application which
which requires you to to have you know a
precise view of the state then that's
that's what you need now there there are
distributed algorithms which provide
something like that they provide you
know perfect consistency on right but
they're slow so so those are kind of the
traditional distributed database
algorithms two-phase commit through this
commit paxos they're in some ways
stronger algorithms but they are you
know depending on the system more more
prone to getting stuck and and you know
giving you giving you nothing or you
know sacrificing availability so so you
have to kind of actually make that
trade-off of you know is it better for
the website to go down sometimes or is
it better for someone to get you know a
scale results sometimes those are kind
of the trade-offs you have to make
unfortunately you do have to make some
trade-off you can't you can't get it off
baltimore relies on a concept called
consistent hashing tell us about that
it's I think a really simple idea that
it's been explained in a complicated way
but the idea is it's it's hashing
meaning you you you make up some
nonsense number or bytes related to your
value and that is gonna control the
location where your value is right so
that's what hashing is in a normal hash
table you would put a you know you would
you would make a little array of size
you know ten or whatever and you enter
things into that array till it gets to
full and then you resize the array and
you copy everything out of that array
into a bigger array right that's how you
know whenever you had your last
implement a hash table not something I
do that anymore but that was that was
how you did it right so the problem with
that becomes it's a great system that's
how most you know in-memory hash tables
work it becomes problematic when when
data is on disk somewhere or over a
network because obviously recopy another
data around would be a big problem if
your hash table is split up onto
multiple machines right so that's that's
exactly the idea so actually this
problem was first encountered with disk
caches which were not distributed it was
just you know instead of a hash table
you have a big file and you would catch
data into the file as opposed to a
a tree or something and they came up
with a totally different solution from
consistent hashing but it provides
similar properties which is you don't
want to have to move all the data you
don't want to have to recopy everything
so in the case of Valdemar we're using
hashing to locate stuff so you know
where is my data oh it's on this machine
that machine and this other machine over
here so we need to be able to answer
that question so there's there's two
ways to answer it one is hashing which
is you kind of predict the location
you'll calculate the location the other
is store the location right you can keep
a big a lookup table and you say okay
well where is such-and-such hashing is
much much easier to scale so that's
that's why we're doing that the the the
problem again becomes you know well okay
when you filled up the machines you have
how can you move data to the other
machines it without moving everything
I'm so so if when I bought my you know I
had ten machines when I bought the
eleventh how can I fill it up without
rearranging everything you'd really like
to move about one tenth of the data in
that case ideally that that's right
that's right so that's that's the
guarantee that or that that's the
property that these consistent hashing
methods provide so a couple ways to go
about it but but essentially what you're
doing is you're you're mapping keys to
some kind of arbitrary partition and
then you're mapping partitions to
machines so the mapping of key to
partition is static but the mapping of
partition to machine is allowed to
change and that allows you to you know
have more flexibility in arranging your
data so we've been talking about these
distributed systems concepts for a few
minutes let's come back to Voldemort
what does a programmer see when they sit
down to write an application that uses
full no more sure so essentially the
model is just like a hash table - you
know maybe you can't you can't iterate
over all the key is quite as easily but
but that's the idea right so so what can
you put in a hash table well you can put
a simple object or you can put a list of
objects or whatever but that's that's
the interface so so for for simple
purposes you can actually mark it out
with an actual hash table and with some
helper class for doing that but
presumably you're going to have
something persistent across multiple
machines when you use it is it the
responsibility of the pro
to take whatever data they have some
complex graph of objects serialize that
and then Voldemort doesn't care what its
storing yes so to some degree so I guess
there's a there's a couple ways to
design this so some people have done
just kind of a dumb byte array so the
system has no idea what it is it's just
bytes it's up to you to get the bytes in
and out correctly other people have kind
of committed to a more traditional data
model where they say okay again I'm
strings you know like we would have in a
database you have our char and you have
big into whatever you know numeric types
and string types you have so the
downside to dumb byte array is it
becomes very hard to peek at your data
if you're the operations team and it
becomes very hard to remember what so
and so put in there when you're the poor
guy who's maintaining so-and-so's code
the downside to you know committing to
an actual schema like you would have in
in my sequel is if you want to do
something crazy like store you know a
personalized search index like for your
personal inbox or if you want to store
like an image then that's obviously not
going to work as naturally in some other
serialization scheme so so that what we
do is we instead kind of make it
pluggable so there's a number of good
serialization systems out there we added
one which has a JSON data model but you
know is a more efficient binary format
but there's a number of good systems out
there there's protocol buffers there's
there's a new one called Avro which is
being used for Hadoop there's thrift
which I think was one of the first open
source ones and so these are these are
pretty good systems they provide some
code generation capabilities they
support the kind of data types you would
want you could store totally opaque data
or if you use one of the provided
silicone the data that's right so in
particular I guess the server knows the
serialization type if you mark it as a
protocol buffer object it will know that
it can be serialize it as a protocol
buffer object so that's that's useful
the the the main reason we went this
kind of middle route is a feature we
just recently added which is views so a
view is I mean a view is a whole thing
in a relational database but for us it
means
just being able to do some server-side
transformation some processing on the
server so in order to do that processing
on the server you need to know what your
bytes me and you can't just you know you
can't just process an opaque byte array
in any meaningful way if any support
provided for an XML data type um
not directly so what we found is XML is
not a great way to store it it's a great
way to store documents we haven't found
it to be a great way to store you know
values all of which will have the same
schema so in particular the the reason
being it's just it's just a bit
inefficient it's it's costly to process
and it's it's costly in terms of the
number of bytes you store but but you
can certainly do that I mean what we
have is essentially a string
serialization type which would allow you
to put it in any string it doesn't you
don't check the XML validation what
programming languages these provide an
API for so the original one was just
Java but we've added a number of others
so we have one for C++ we have one for
Python and we have one for Ruby and if
anybody else knows another language it
wants to write it's it's not too hard to
do and it's nice it makes it accessible
to people in other languages
project voldemort implemented entirely
in Java yeah yeah I mean only only the
other clients are in you know outside of
Java now we're going to talk about the
architecture could you break it into
pieces for us at the high level and tell
us what the pieces are and how they work
together yeah sure so I mean there's a
couple of problems you have to solve one
is is where to put your stuff which
which machines are going to hold what
and so that we talked about the
consistent hashing that's kind of the
routing layer it's gonna deal with the
fact that there's multiple machines that
each read or write needs to go to it's
gonna choose those machines using
consistent hashing or some other it's
actually pluggable so if you have a
different hashing mechanism you could
you could kind of implement your own I
know their problem you're gonna have to
do it solve this is you know getting
data back and forth over the network as
quickly as possible so there's there's
kind of a networking or remoting there
and there there's a storage layer which
is you know
where are my bytes on this machine are
they are they in memory on that and just
how can I get at them
so so those are the those are kind of
the main layers the things that are
happening at the routing layer is you
know choosing the machines a thing goes
to getting back all the results
repairing any inconsistent data on those
machines and you know handing handing
back the the single result to the client
the the network layer is just you know
kind of very simple socket access we
have also an HTTP version of that layer
but hasn't proven to be greatly
beneficial because it's a bit slower if
I had a programming language I wanted to
use it you didn't have a client for I
could use the HTTP correct um you could
there's still some stuff you'll need to
understand there's there's some
versioning of the data which which
you'll need to kind of deserialize so
even if you're even if you're
communicating to be a HTTP you still
need to be able to understand the
versioning of the data and what what
values you're getting back so it's not
you know it's not the simplest kind of
restful model but it is much more
efficient than you know me giving you
back a a XML description of whatever you
know so so that was kind of the
trade-off was since we felt like this
was a you know a storage system is
inherently strongly coupled to the
application it's not something that it's
going to be kind of publicly accessible
on the internet it's you know it's
inside of your application we felt like
you know there's more important for it
to be fast then then do something more
restful which would provide the the most
easiest compatibility model with every
other language but would have other
drawbacks so you were partway through
the layers and I asked you that question
so it's yes yeah okay so that's what the
network layer is doing the the
persistence layer is is probably the
thing that the most thought in databases
has ever gone into is you know what's
what's the data structure for this in
practice
everyone has ended up with B trees but
there's a lot of other stuff out there
in particular kind of variants which are
more like a log structured file system
that kind of right ahead what we're
using at LinkedIn is something based on
B to B is Java audition so they have a
very good kind of right ahead B tree
implementation we DB that is Berkeley
database
yeah that's Berkeley database or
sleepycat I guess some people call it
because that was the company that made
it so that's that's what we're using the
most the other thing that we have is is
something which is probably more
efficient than that for kind of
read-only batch computed data and then
we've we've done a number of experiments
to try to you know the idea of having a
kind of pluggable layer for this is
there there are real trade-offs that
have to do with how many writes you have
how many reads you have what are the
size of the values and a number of other
things like that you know how variable
is the request stream so we've we've
done kind of a number of experiments on
improving this and I think we haven't
gotten something we're completely happy
with as a solution to be to be like it
just isn't as good all around
so we've stuck with that for now the
ordering of the layers is not
necessarily fixed there's some
flexibility in the type of network
architecture you choose and how you
arrange the layers what are the choices
that you have there in particular one
thing we did when we we built this which
you know it has some some advantages and
disadvantages is we tried to build each
layer as kind of a decoration on top of
the other layer which means you can
actually reverse the layers to some
degree so clearly you need to serialize
your data before you send it over a
network you know you need to turn it
into bytes before you can send it over a
network or put it on a disk but you it
is actually possible to to reverse
things like routing and network which
which has some interesting trade-offs in
particular it can make it so that you
can have a very dumb kind of client and
the dumb client just you know sends the
data to whichever server it knows about
and that server sends the data to the
right places or you can have a smarter
client which has has one less hop and
just sends the data directly to the the
the servers that will be you know
eventually storing this so the the
trade-off has to do with you know the
the implementation complexity of the
client versus you know kind of the
latency in in performance and also how
tightly coupled the client is to the
server in what situation would you want
to put the routing on the client rather
than on the server when you can it makes
sense
it makes sense to spread the load to the
client and avoid the network hop just
because the what you pay for the network
hop is is probably not worth it so I
guess currently today it makes sense to
do that if you're doing it in Java or
C++ because those are what we have a
rich client for so for a LinkedIn that's
what that's what we're doing we've had
we've had pretty good results for that
what software runs on a server node in a
cluster so so essentially there's you
know kind of a server process it can be
deployed as like a war in a servlet
container also if that's better you know
for your setup and what that's gonna
have is it's gonna have the the storage
layer the storage engine that we talked
about it's gonna have a you know the
network server or servers if you have
both the you know tcp/ip and HTTP
servers configured and and it's gonna
have some other background consistency
stuff so we have a kind of
administrative API we have you know a
few other things which are you know
running in the background that might do
background cleaning other data and stuff
but that's the main software on the
server so and in addition we're gonna
have kind of this this routing layer for
doing server side routing which is kind
of sits in the background waits for a
request which is you know as yet
unrouted and then we'll send to the
right servers from there are there any
distinguished nodes in the network that
plays a special role or are they all
uniform yes so one of the decisions we
made and it has a real trade-offs is is
that all the nodes are uniform so it's
it's completely appears there's nothing
different you know the only thing that
distinguishes one from the other is its
its ID there's no there's no master
there's no election of masters so that
makes certain problems a little bit
harder and then certain problems a lot
easier so in particular we think it's a
lot easier to operate that kind of a
system because you don't have this you
know special node or tiers so so other
systems I've seen that some of which are
very good have you know a very layered
architecture with five or six components
which are actually in completely
different programming languages and work
differently and they fulfill some role
in the system
we don't have that we just have a bunch
of computers which are all identical and
they may be doing one or two different
types of things but all the notes
already from an operational standpoint
that's simple usually it you know I mean
in particular if you have if you have
six different pieces all performing some
role then your your operations team is
gonna need to know what all the pieces
are how they work together how they talk
to each other and you then need to you
know you have six possible bottlenecks
if you can if you can do it in such a
way that you just have one type of
machine then you're you're only
bottleneck because you know how many how
many machines do we have hopefully can
you add or remove nodes from a live
system and have the system is the system
self-organizing yeah so that's something
we're working on so we haven't really
had that feature or I mean rather you
can always add data to a system but it
would your data would become kind of
like unavailable you know that that key
would be the consistency guarantees
would be lost while it was being moved
right so so we haven't we haven't really
had that feature implemented correctly
and so that's that's something we're
working on I think we almost have it we
have kind of like in in trunk now we
have kind of a very very alpha version
of it and so the the main the main
features we needed to get that was the
ability to stream data between machines
efficiently you can't just do you know a
million puts and gets to move data you
have to stream it efficiently and also
the ability to kind of change some of
the metadata on the fly and expire the
metadata the clients have so that they
now talk to the right machines and so on
without that feature then if you want to
increase the size of a cluster do you
need to take it down and run some kind
of a script to reorganize the data yeah
do people typically build clusters out
of homogeneous hardware or can the
system use different sized hardware
efficiently so it can use different size
hardware efficiently whether or not that
makes sense is another question so we we
are we are doing that to some extent but
I think we're trying not to so what we
have the ability to do is is keep more
or less data on up
machine and in practice that will affect
a few things right so it will affect how
much disk space you're using how much I
owe and you know kind of i/o operations
you're gonna have and it will also
affect how many Network requests you get
how much CPU you get because that's the
number of overall requests you're gonna
get so that's kind of the tuning knob
for supporting different hardware now in
practice that may be a bit of a pain to
manage if you have to remember oh you
know no.21 has extra stuff because it
has you know seven hard drives and
they're fast in 22 has two hard drives
and this really slow so it has less
stuff it also kind of makes the
performance of the system hard to
characterize because you know if you if
you draw your monitoring graph saying
this one's different than that one
that's it's a bit of a pain but you may
turn out to be a good feature so yeah we
support it but we're trying not to use
it at LinkedIn just because it's easier
to manage homogeneous system do you have
any modeling tips for anticipating the
size of a cluster that I'm gonna need
before building it yeah so it's actually
kind of an easy problem
so usually performance tuning for
storage stuff is very difficult the
reason is in general the variance of i/o
is very high you have your your actual
disk operations which are extremely slow
and then you have your cache disk
operations which are instantaneous and
so you have some mixture of those and
you don't quite know what you're gonna
get for a particular query but but since
we're only providing a very limited set
of fast API so it's pretty predictable
so the things that you need to
understand are what percentage of my hot
data is in memory so the best way to
estimate that is what percentage of all
the data is in memory right so if you
have let's say you have a terabyte of
data and you cut it up among ten
machines and then you you store two
copies of everything or three copies of
everything it's pretty easy to figure
out okay how much data is there on each
machine right and then the other
question you would ask is well how much
memory do I have on those machines and
that's kind of the raw proportion of
data you would have in memory if there
was no locality of reference or whatever
so so if you're if you're running at a
ratio of you know 50% in memory you
would expect pretty quick in terms of
performing
if you're if you're running at a rate of
you know ten to one on disk then then
you would expect much slower right
because most the time you're gonna be
doing a ten mohs second disc seek to
find your stuff so that's kind of the
basic guideline in if you want to try a
real problem the way we always do it is
we say okay well roughly how big is my
value and then we try it and we see the
performance and then we extrapolate out
so if I had you know because it scales
linearly you can say okay well this is
performance for this many on one machine
if I had five more like that this is be
what I would see so so we essentially
hold that ratio fixed and then you know
multiply out by the actual amount of
data and the actual amount of machines
and that's that's been pretty realistic
I mean you know there's always some
surprise but it's you know you're
expecting more like plus plus or minus
ten percent rather than you know oh my
god I have a full table scan and nothing
works at all this seems to me an
advantage of this type system compared
to relational databases which scale very
non linearly yes so so in practice I
think it's one of the biggest advantages
that if at least for us if we're in the
process of developing a feature you can
think before you've written any code you
can you know take out your notebook and
you can do a few paper and pencil
calculations which will give you a very
accurate estimate of how feasible is
what you're doing what are the hardware
requirements going to be and knowing
that very early on in the process
instead of right at the end when it's
all done and it's too late to order any
hardware anyway that's hugely
advantageous because then you can you
can rethink about some of your
requirements or whatever if it turns out
that you know it's just an unfeasible
problem to solve or you can you can buy
more machines or whatever you need to do
early on let's walk through what happens
when you do or right okay yes so so I
mean it's it's fairly straightforward
I'll walk you through it with the the
client-side router so essentially you
know you're gonna call put and you're
gonna pass in you know kind of a key and
a value it's it's going to hear your
value is going to be serialized in two
bytes
if you've enabled compression it's going
to be compressed
and then the routing layer is going to
take that value it's gonna it's gonna
take your key it's going to calculate
you know which which machines might
might have this you know are responsible
for this and the the order to do the
writes in and it's then going to hand
those off to the the lower level kind of
network stores which are going to start
doing these rights to all the machines
and then you know each each the network
request gets sent to the individual
machines the machines you know do you
sterilize the network request and and
perform the right to disk
how many rights does it do of each piece
of data that's a configuration option so
what you want kind of depends on what
what performance you're hoping for so
the the there's a couple there's a
couple of knobs that you have
so the first knob is you know how many
times is each value written overall so
that that's obviously going to control
how many machines you can you can have
down and still get your data right so if
you write it three times and and you
lose three machines then somebody's
missing their stuff the the other knob
is is how much do you the the person
calling put how many of those rights do
you wait for so right you might you
might not care at all in which case you
maybe you wait for no rights or you
might wait for just you know the first
right to occur the second right to occur
before you consider it going I'm coming
to you with a application that I want to
build what are some questions you'd ask
me to determine how to set those knobs
appropriately for my application sure so
I mean I guess the the the primary thing
that I asked is what you know what are
what are the expectations for the data
you know what is the data is is it
something a user took time to enter or
is it something that we've just
calculated typically something that you
know your user has has created is is
pretty valuable and you don't want to
lose it maybe something that you've
calculated is kind of less valuable and
and so that's that's usually it's you
know what what how important is this how
important is this data the more
important it is the more the more
correct the more correctness guarantee
you want right
or replicas the more rights you wait for
that's gonna introduce latency from the
user standpoint correct that's correct
yeah and it will increase the the load
on the system right so if you if you if
you do twice as many rights you'll have
twice as much load from those rights now
what happens when you want to read the
data so essentially the same thing will
happen the key will be serialized the
routing layer will choose the you know
the same nodes that you wrote it to
you'll perform you'll perform a read
from some number of those nodes which is
again a configuration property those
requests will be sent off to those
machines the machines will you know look
it up in the storage engine and provide
a result the the result comes back with
a version attached to it so then on the
client side or whoever's doing the
routing if it's server side routing this
would happen on the whichever server was
processing your request the versions
will all be compared any version which
is kind of obsolete will be scheduled to
get repaired but doing multiple reads
yeah and looking for the best one that's
right that's right so so so essentially
this kind of a system is actually
postponing the consistency meaning it's
not consistent immediately on right but
we guarantee the consistency properties
whatever you've kind of set on read
meaning you have to go to more than one
place if you want that kind of read your
own writes consistency so so yeah it's
going to do multiple multiple reads
maybe on a two or three it's going to
compare the versions on those objects
you're gonna get returned the most
up-to-date and it's gonna schedule a
repair on anybody who's out-of-date what
is a repair it's just a put operation so
so let's say that let's say that you
know one machine was down or had some
error or for some reason couldn't get
there earlier right
well what happens then clearly it needs
to get the right value eventually so
there's a couple mechanisms by what you
can get which you can get that but the
simplest is if you just do a read we get
back three three versions and one of
them is is old then we can schedule you
know put operation that will happen in
the background and update that value
all rights guaranteed to finish within
any
found an amount of time yes so all the
operations come with a timeout so I mean
one thing we found is for real-time
applications it's usually better to fail
in a guaranteed amount of time than to
always succeed eventually so so in
particular if you have a webpage and you
know maybe your web pages does 10 or 20
or 50 or 100 service requests to get all
the information it needs it's really
important that you have some kind of
fixed guarantee of how long each of
those pieces takes otherwise you know
even a very trivial piece can break the
whole thing you know you're as slow as
your slowest component so so we each
each kind of operation has a timeout and
when that timeouts reached the operation
will fail even if it might have
succeeded had you waited longer that
enables application developers to write
applications with some kind of latency
guarantee that's right so in particular
it lets you tolerate slowness on a
single machine a little better so we try
to do as good as we can without it's one
of the harder problems but in particular
what you would like I mean you know
typical application if you if you have
one database and your database is slow
than your application is slow right what
you would like if you have more than one
server is you would like to be you know
not as slow as your slowest machine you
would like to somehow know that that
machine was slow and not use it so so
what we have in place is this kind of an
SLA that you set and you say okay the
most must happen within this time period
if it doesn't that machine is going to
be taken out and only periodically used
to retry it to see if it's fixed itself
if I do a read or write then there are
multiple machines if enough of them
finish the operation will complete and
the client can continue that's right so
you get your result back as quick as the
as quick as the you know the fastest two
or three or however many you've
configured that you must have opposed I
configure it to return from a write when
zero storages have completed because I
don't exactly care what happens on the
back end is the storage layer guaranteed
to finish persisting things to a
permanent state within any bounded
amount of time no yeah so you if you
don't wait then you have no Guerin
is whatsoever of what happened right so
so it could be for example that the
client you were on lost all network
capabilities you know the the very
instant that you called put and so no no
rights were done whatsoever and there's
nothing there's nothing that can be done
about that so you have to wait for for
some rights to occur before you have any
Gogi now a second question you have this
Windows data actually get to disk it's a
important question so so the the the
interface within our system is that it's
up to the store agenda to decide so you
can write up purely in memory storage
engine of course when you restart this
server it will will lose your stuff so
you have to be aware of that we do have
such a thing but but I think it's
probably not that practical for usage
but in particular one of the the huge
performance benefits of a system like
this is not not writing your data to
disk immediately so what that means is a
your rights can be they can be done and
kind of an append-only fashion and they
it can happen kind of when when when
many rights have accumulated you can you
can kind of do a single update to disk
rather than doing random rights all over
the place and so that's that's that's
that's the first benefit is the disk
improves but also the latency ever right
is much better so so in particular if
you're waiting for you know a single
disk C plus right you're talking
probably at least 10 milliseconds if
you're waiting for that on multiple
machines then you're waiting for the the
longer of these operations right because
you you know even that the 10
milliseconds assumes that you start
right away but you may be waiting for
other writes to complete or whatever
else so so if you're taking the maximum
of three of those or something maybe
much worse so you want to a you know we
would want to avoid that for our
production systems we usually see you
know very good very good performance so
from client side could be you know
millisecond and five milliseconds per
right so it's you know it's faster than
a disk seek from the client side even
though that includes Network overhead
serialization and the designer needs to
make some choices then about the number
of reads and the number of writes which
you could look at independently of each
other but is there any significant
to the number of reads in comparison to
the number of writes yeah so I mean the
the the two important guidelines are a
you know really do put it on more than
one machine even though you're not used
to that with a database it's just most
of the features don't work if it's only
if everything is only written to one
machine because we have that machine
fails and has a disk error the data is
really gone number of writes greater
than greater than greater than or equal
to two sorry strictly greater than one
so we found first of all people who
thought that was a good idea was not a
good idea probably three is the right
number I don't know why but two seems to
be slightly too little because sometimes
you do actually have two machines that
fell at the same time and then that's
you know you don't want to have to if
you're waiting for a new machine to come
in or something or somebody doesn't have
time to deal with it you don't want to
have to deal with that right away the
other thing is you know the the
consistency guarantee of reading your
own writes that would require that you
know the number of reads plus the number
of writes is is at least the the number
of replicas so so if you you you what
I'm saying is you can configure it in
such a way that you're you're guaranteed
to always read one of the the newer
versions that you wrote you're never
going to have a situation where there's
no overlap between those two so if you
do that you're gonna get back what you
what you put in which is usually what
what people want the system designed
under the assumption that failures are
short and machine boots back up pretty
quickly um no no so so in particular we
don't have that very often if we don't
sometimes we have we have extra hardware
meaning if a machine fails it's you can
swap in such and such and there's two
kinds of failures one one kind of
failure is like oh we're just pushing
new code so we we do a rolling restart
across the server's the system stays up
but a particular server is down for for
a few seconds or you know few minutes
but another kind of server is like well
I know that kind of problem is I don't
know we had some problems with raid
controllers and we had some problems
with disk or whatever and the server's
actually down for hours or in some cases
you know we
and so in that case yeah it's definitely
down for a extended period of time the
relational database we push most of the
computation out to the server it
understands all the data it knows how
it's structured from what you're saying
with this application you have some
decisions to make about do you want to
do more of this processing on the client
or on the server huh
how do you think about that so most of
the time there's there's not a problem
it's fine to just yes and the data at
the client let the client deal with it
the the real case where you get into
trouble is if you just want a little
snippet of that data or you're going to
somehow aggregate the data maybe by
maybe you want to count everything that
meets some criteria these are things
which are kind of very traditional
sequel uses you know where X greater
than 2 and whatever right so the first
assumption is you know because this is
kind of a key value storage you've
already denormalized that you have some
blob that has the stuff you want but but
you might say well it's it's sort of
inefficient for you to transform you the
whole blob then mean to filter out just
the things which meet my criteria come
up with a single little integer which
counseled them all and then use that
right because you transferred me maybe
you know 50 kilobytes but I only
computed something that was you know 4
bytes long in the end so your complaint
would be well you know it's stupid for
for for you to send me all these
kilobytes I should just you know send my
code over to you once you do that on
your side and and that would be more
efficient now in practice network is not
always the bottleneck so may or may not
actually make anything faster but it
does make it does make sense to do this
in a lot of cases in particular we say
that you know our storage nodes are
usually not CPU bound so so they have
additional CPU capacity and it's always
nice to have have less network i/o it's
always nice to to speed things up that
way so so so that's the scenario where
you'd want to kind of create a view
which has your code now the downside to
that is you you're kind of coupling your
application a bit more strongly to the
to the system I guess in that in that
respect
it's kinda like a stored procedure as
much as a view right because you've
you've sent some piece of your
application over to the the database
server which is now performing that for
you so is that a good thing well it may
it may reduce the the amount of data
that's transferred back and forth a view
is a computation that you want performed
on the server from a voldemort yeah yeah
so the primary reason you would do that
is to avoid Network IO the server needs
to understand at least something about
how your data is organized in order to
implement a view that's correct
otherwise you would just have a bunch of
bytes and it would be up to you to kind
of get it right obviously that could be
very difficult to do so
so because you you know when you create
the the way it's organized is this it's
not just one you know the whole cluster
of machines is not just one hash table
it's kind of like multiple hash tables
each hash table has specific settings
about the number of reads and writes and
other things like that one of those
settings is what's the serialization
type for this data and so that that kind
of guarantees that whenever you interact
with that data it's it's correctly
serialized you don't have you can't
accidentally serialize it into the wrong
thing and get some done since data back
so so as a result of having that
metadata associated with the store we
can correctly serialize the data on the
server and apply the users view
transformation to it and then give give
back at the transformed result you say
that the system has multiple hash tables
that would be in a relational database
like the customer table table count
tables tables so I guess I didn't call
them tables just because they're not
tabular but in fact that's much more
straightforward
we called them stores because they're
non tabular but but yeah they're just
tables does the view functionality
extend to being able to join across
separate stores or tables so no no it
doesn't right so I guess the if if
you're going to join data you're going
to go across the network because the
data you're going to cut across what's
on a particular machine because the data
is partitioned up amongst machines and
if you're doing that there's no real
savings of pushing it to
pushing it to the server side because
the server is gonna have to go you know
to multiple machines and transfer the
data across their network anyway now
that said that's that's a perfectly fine
thing to do and in fact as you know very
common use cases could you do a bunch of
gets four different things and kind of
assemble it all into one this would put
on the client the burden of what a query
optimizer does in a relational database
um yes yes it does yes so so whether or
not you think that's a good thing kind
of depends my perspective that this is
all online
I have also spent a lot of time on
offline systems in particular you know
we have kind of Hadoop and we have a
bunch of these distributed databases
we've tried a couple of them we have
Astra data right now and they're they're
selling point is always the query
optimizer and my pain point is always
the quieter because Hadoop has no query
optimizer so you just tell it to do
something and it does it and if you tell
it something stupid you know oh this is
the stupid thing stop doing that and so
I found especially for kind of a
real-time website you need to know what
it's doing you know if it optimizes it
wrong and you get something which would
scan every table across you know 20
machines or something that will
completely crash your site and you know
that's a terrible terrible bug and see
it needs to be you need to somehow be
able to program things in a way that the
optimizer couldn't choose that and so as
a result I'm not a huge believer in that
problem I think it's a very fun computer
science problem because it's there's no
right answer and you know you so you can
always work on it and write more papers
about how to optimize that particular
case better but I think in practice for
a system you're better off thinking
about the problem in understanding your
your data and then making making a good
decision what you're saying now is that
things that we wish were hidden and that
are hidden in a small system are not
really hidden in a large system even if
you have some part of the system that's
claiming to do that for you yeah so I
guess I guess the another way to say the
same thing that's true and another way
to say the same thing is that the this
these kind of key value stores they're
there they're hiding things which were
not hidden before like the
database servers you have and that kind
of stuff so it's making it some in some
ways it's a higher level system that's
not making you think about that
but other things are lower level like
like how you're doing your table
operations is now lower level because
you you're breaking it down into very
predictable operations on multiple
stores which previously would be hidden
from you and just batched up into one
declarative statement so it's kind of
simultaneously I think getting higher
level and level at the same time the one
kind of unifying theme is it's it's
bringing the API more in line with the
what the machines can provide
performance wise so so I guess I like to
think about databases versus the file
system API file system API is a bit of a
pain to work with but it provides
exactly what disks and files can provide
in terms of performance meaning you can
seek and you expect when you call seek
you expect that to take some time when
you open a file you expect a certain
amount of time for that so it hasn't
abstracted over anything but it's
extremely you know predictable versus
database query where you know you're
gonna have one sentence of text it may
take an hour it might take you know a
millisecond it's very hard to tell by
looking at it which of those two it
would be are there integration layers
that make it easy to plug Voldemort in
in place of a relational database with
rails or spring or any of the more
popular web frameworks so probably not I
mean I think the way these things come
about is something becomes very standard
and then people figure out what the pain
points are and then they develop great
great libraries that kind of work around
those pain points so I think for all
these new databases there's not that
much I mean you know there I have seen a
few little things here there but I think
they're they're probably not nearly
mature enough that it's really doing
anything for you that you couldn't do
yourself rather quickly so I mean
obviously integrates with spring fairly
easily there's no kind of ORN solution
that will you know transparently map
everything for you
now now primarily I think the reason for
that and certainly the reason we haven't
focused on it is because the use case
that we have
we're not using the rme either just
because you know once you've kind of
split your thing into services there's
not a very complicated mapping between
between objects and relations anymore
it's actually kind of a simpler mapping
and then you're calling lots of API so
you have a an object API mapping problem
not a object relational mapping problem
if that makes sense because because like
for a service oriented architecture your
your integration point is api's rather
than tables so versus if you have like
you know a very simple application where
you have a single database with a bunch
of tables then you're trying to figure
out how to piece together all those
tables into your domain model so for
that reason we haven't we haven't done
any work on that it would be interesting
to see what people come up with it's
obviously going to be a little bit more
difficult to do because a database can
provide you a very inefficient query for
anything whereas these systems kind of
only have efficient ways that's all
there is so so if you haven't provided
the right structure for the lookup you
actually can't you can't do it versus a
database you would just do it and then
you would notice Oh such-and-such page
is slow Y and then you'd figure it out
and you would put it in the right index
or whatever to make it faster would it
make sense to use Voldemort to store
session data that the user needs to
retain from one page view to the next
when you're in a clustered environment
mmm yeah yeah that's that's a perfectly
valid use case are you very familiar
with uses of Voldemort outside of
LinkedIn um I'm a little bit familiar
I become familiar if something doesn't
work because then people email to do X Y
doesn't you know I expect to see Y but I
don't what's going on but yes I mean
what I've seen is basically web
companies and gaming companies seem to
use it they seem to be the people who
have real time problems with you know
enough data to bother looking outside of
like my sequel so it's usually fairly
small cluster of machines you know maybe
half dozen dozen machines
there's their small company so that's
that's that's probably funny if you have
an idea what are some of the larger
clusters that people are building yeah
it's probably not well outside of that
range I mean for a LinkedIn it's usually
like you know maybe ten machines or
something as a cluster somewhere
somewhere much smaller than that so so I
think you know it's the the goal of
course was to have as few as possible
so we've gone with a system where we
have you know kind of like three or four
separate clusters which are completely
isolated from each other and then a
bunch of features grouped together on on
one cluster that doesn't they're suppose
I want to move all my data out of
Baltimore into a data warehouse so we
can do some offline analytics where we
take advantage of the capabilities of
the more rich query language are there
some tools to help with that process
yeah there are probably not as not as
many as we would like a lot of these
integration and pulling technologies
take time to develop first you have to
have a very stable system then people
spend time integrating it in all
different ways and then you get a good
set of solutions for different problems
so what we have right now is kind of a
batch streaming API that will let you
stream your data into Hadoop or whatever
what we don't have that I would love to
have and it's kind of our next step is a
good set of MapReduce jobs that work
with any data type and kind of act as an
input format or something to to get you
all your stuff out of your Baltimore
cluster and likewise it would be nice to
have kind of a catch-up mechanism such
that you only get the updates from
yesterday you don't have to kind of re
read transfer everything so those are
those are kind of the two missing
features what I'm hearing from you in
response to solve all of these questions
is this is a fairly new technology and
all the complimentary pieces aren't
there yet but there's a lot of scope for
obvious improvements yeah so I think
that that would be true I mean for for
databases and file systems it's kind of
a decade-long project and so so my
advice to people if they're looking at
this for something in their products
would be you know if you don't have a
problem then you don't have a problem
just stick with whatever you've got
because most of things that which have
been out for 10 years or more are going
to have a
a lot of things built up around them
that you may not you may not realize you
would be missing with anything newer
that said if you do have a problem
probably these systems are much gonna be
much better and have a lot more
infrastructure built up around them than
doing it yourself which of course then
you'll have nothing so that's that's
kind of the trade-off if you're thinking
about doing it yourself then then
probably this will help you a lot and
provide a lot more built up
infrastructure if you're if you're
thinking about just using my sink well
then you know that's that's a pretty
good solution if that will if that will
get the job done
tell us about how the voldemort project
is organized as an open-source project
it's loosely organized
I mean basically what we have is we have
maybe three or four people in LinkedIn
who are doing a lot of work and then we
have maybe three or four people outside
of LinkedIn who are doing a lot of work
and then we have a lot of people who
seems to be kind of trying it or using
it right so people who are trying it or
using it give great feedback later okay
you know so and so just committed to X
and now why doesn't work anymore
please fix immediately that's that's
very useful feedback to get the
organization you know among people you
know writing code is kind of like
whatever you know people who are not
working for for linked and I'm gonna do
whatever they need
I think there's pretty good consensus
among all the people of what what we
think is you know we would most want and
then LinkedIn is kind of funding the
features that we need which you know
around monitoring and scaling and the
ETL problems you described and other
stuff like that that just make it fit
into our environment better LinkedIn
then is the primary industry sponsor of
the project yeah I think so in the that
we're you know the we're putting the
most people to work on it full-time for
some open source products there's
commercial entities that will provide
support as a business does anything like
that exists for voldemort yeah yeah yeah
so I mean LinkedIn is not a database
company so you know you can definitely
get a lot of help from people on the
mailing list but ultimately there's no
kind of organization that you can sue if
there's so so that that that you know
there's no kind of 24/7 support or
whatever contract that you can buy so
that's that's also something to think
about
does the prod
there are many patches from the
community yeah so we get we get you know
kind of outside of people who are doing
work all the time I think we get a lot
of just random patches that fix
so-and-so or make such and such
command-line and easier to use or add
support for some new compression type or
whatever and those are those are very
helpful where would people go if they
want to learn more or maybe get involved
there's a website that's project -
Baltimore comm and there's also a
mailing list it's linked off the website
and show you can always you can always
ask you know questions on that mailing
list if you're having trouble setting
something up or your you're not seeing
what you expect there's there's kind of
a list of of what we thought were fun
projects on the website so if you're if
you're like interested in this stuff and
you want to you know take on some
project and try it out there's a list of
things that were you know not too hard
as to be unachievable but also pretty
interesting and so you can check that
out and see okay you know if you had a
couple days to play around with it you
can try out one of these projects what
are some of the fun projects you'd like
to see done there's lots of them so that
I mentioned the kind of Hadoop
integration where we you know write the
MapReduce job that that pulls all the
data out
that's as yet undone there's niño
improvements on the client
there's views where one that I just did
so I need to take that off so some of
the fun projects we get around to you
and then let's see what else do we have
there's there's a bunch of smaller
improvements for the read-only storage
engine and implementation of kind of
other replication mechanisms to be able
to catch up you know from a particular
point like if let's say you have a
search engine you want to index
everything that goes in you need to have
a subscription mechanism to to keep up
with changes so there's a there's a
there's a bunch of features like that
those are the ones that that I remember
off the top of my head anyway do you
write or blog anywhere if people would
like to follow what you're thinking
about I haven't done that much recently
I mean basically working on this project
and we have a couple other open-source
projects coming out and then I work at a
startup
as well so I have you know a bunch of
features I'm working I'm keeping the web
working I haven't had time to do much
there is a blog for Project Baltimore so
I have anything related to that I have
post pretty recently
on different features or stuff we're
working on and I think we're going to
expand that as we add our team has to
right now maybe three or four open
source projects and we have a couple
more coming out so we're maybe going to
make it a little bit more general
purpose to talk about stuff in that area
that that's being done but yeah nothing
nothing much outside of that I don't
have a Twitter account yet so how can
people reach you if they'd like to ask
you anything so you can email me I'm J
dot crepes gmail and I try to get back
there as soon as possible that's
definite J crepes thank you very much
for being on software engineering radio
thank you for having me thanks for
listening to software engineering radio
software engineer radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the AC radio team
by our website or you can advertise for
se radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious links and the
slash dot button to contact the team
please send email to team at SC - radio
net or if they're specific to an episode
please use the comments facility on the
website so other people can react to
your comments this episode of se radio
as well as all other episodes are
licensed under the creative commons 2.5
license please see the website for
details thanks to Charlie Crowell and
the portside Music Network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas our workshop